Subtitles downloaded from Podnapisi.NET
[ Chanting in arabic ]
[ Tick tick tick ]
[ Tick tick ti- - ]
[ Hoofbeats ]
[ Pebbles falling ]
[ Growling ]
[ Dogs growling ]
[ Dogs barking ]
[ Crash ]
[ Rattle rattle ]
[ Cars honking ]
[ Crash ]
Sure do love you .
Morning .
Good morning , Mrs. MacNeil .
How are you today ?
Fine . Thank you .
That 's good .
It 's ok . I 've got it . Thanks .
Good morning , madam .
Good morning , Karl .
Oh , Karl , we 've got rats in the attic .
You better get some traps .
Rats ?
Hh-hmm . I 'm afraid so .
But the attic is clean .
All right , then we 've got clean rats .
No . No rats .
I just heard them , Karl .
Maybe plumbing .
Yeah , or maybe rats .
Now will you just get the traps ?
Yes , I go now .
Don 't go now , Karl . The stores aren 't open yet .
I will see .
They 're closed .
Man over bullhorn : In the group over here ,
I need a priest , a nun , and two students .
That 's exactly what we want .
... and the camera goes around here .
Burke ?
Oh , Burke .
Is the scene really essential , Burke ?
Would you do without it ?
This damn thing doesn 't make sense .
It 's perfectly plain . You 're a teacher .
You don 't want the building torn down .
Come on , I can read .
Well , what 's wrong ?
Well , why are they tearing the building down ?
Shall we summon the writer ?
He 's in Paris , I believe .
Hiding ?
Fucking !
Scene 39 , hotel . Take 4 .
All right , hustle , background , and action !
[ Roar of protesters ]
Girl : We 're not backing down !
Director : And action , Chris !
[ Feedback ]
Wait a minute !
Wait . Hold it . Hey , come on .
We 're all concerned with human rights ,
for God 's sakes .
But the kids who want to get education
have a right , too !
Yeah ! Yeah !
Don 't you understand ?
It 's against your own principle ,
for God 's sake !
Yeah ! Yeah !
You can 't accomplish anything
by shutting kids out of their school .
Yeah ! Yeah !
Hold it ! Hold it !
If you want to effect any change ,
you have to do it within the system .
Director : Ok , cut . That 's a wrap .
I think I 'll walk home tonight , Mike .
Take that and drop it by my house .
Good night , tom .
Good night .
There 's not a day in my life
that I don 't feel like a fraud .
Priests , doctors , lawyers- - I 've talked to them all .
I don 't know anyone who hasn 't felt that .
[ Airplane flies over ]
Hello ?
In here .
Hi . How did your day go ?
Not too bad . It was like the Walt Disney version
of the ho chi minh story ,
but other than that , it was terrific .
What have we got ? Anything exciting here ?
Also , you got an invitation .
What 's this ?
Dinner at the white house .
You 're kidding me .
Is it a big party or something ?
Just 5 or 6 people .
Thursday , huh ?
Far out .
Girl : Hi , mom .
What did you do today ?
Stuff .
What 's that mean , " stuff " ?
Well , me and Sharon played a game
in the backyard ,
and we had a picnic down by the river .
That sounds fun .
You should have seen this man came along
on this beautiful gray horse .
Really what kind ?
Was it a mare , a gelding , what ?
I think it was a gelding .
It was gray . It was so beautiful .
The guy let me ride it all around .
Oh , that 's nice .
It was so nice . Oh , I loved it .
Mom , can 't we get a horse ?
Not while we 're in Washington .
We 'll see when we get home , ok ?
When can I have one ?
We 'll see , Regan . We 'll see .
On the party invitations , I want- -
Regan , don 't .
Regan , come back here .
You 're in--come here .
Ha ha ha !
All right , give it up .
No !
Oh ! You 'll be sorry .
Father ...
Would you help an old altar boy ?
I 'm a catholic .
All right . Come on , man .
Alfonso !
Hey , man !
[ People speaking Greek on radio ]
Mama ?
Mama .
Dimmie .
[ Speaking Greek ]
How are you , mama ?
I 'm so glad to see you .
You look good .
I 'm all right .
How 's your leg ?
How about you ?
Fine , mama . I 'm fine .
[ Speaking Greek ]
Your Uncle John
passed by to visit me .
Oh , really ? When ?
Last month .
Too tight ?
No .
Mama , you have to stay off it .
You can 't go up and down the stairs .
You have to give it a rest .
Ok .
Mama , I could take you somewhere
where you would be safe and wouldn 't be alone .
There would be people around .
You wouldn 't be sitting here
listening to a radio .
[ Speaking Greek ]
You understand me ?
This is my house ,
and I 'm not going no place .
Dimmie , you worry for something .
No , mama .
You are not happy .
Tell me , what is the matter ?
Mama , I 'm all right .
I 'm fine , really I am .
[ Tunes radio to Greek music ]
Here it comes .
There .
Look at that .
You like it ?
Oh , isn 't that funny ?
I better put him over here to dry , though .
He 's still wet .
There . He can dry there .
Hey , where did this come from ?
I found it .
Where ?
The closet .
Huh .
Have you been playing with it ?
Yep .
You know how ?
I 'll show you .
Wait a minute . You need 2 .
No , you don 't . I do it all the time .
Oh , yeah ? Well , let 's both play .
You really don 't want me to play , huh ?
No , I do . Captain howdy said no .
Captain who ?
Captain howdy .
Who 's captain howdy ?
I make the questions , and he does the answers .
Oh ...
Captain howdy , ah , I see .
He 's nice .
Oh , I 'll bet he is .
Here , I 'll show you .
Captain howdy ,
do you think my mom 's pretty ?
Captain howdy ?
Captain howdy ,
that isn 't very nice .
Well , maybe he 's sleeping .
You think ?
What--Regan ...
Why are you reading that stuff ?
Because I like it .
It 's not even a good picture of you .
You look so mature .
I wouldn 't talk .
You wouldn 't talk ?
Well , I didn 't have my makeup man there .
Let me take an eyelash off your face .
No , I didn 't get it .
What are we going to do on your birthday ?
Isn 't it nice
it 's on Sunday this year ?
What can we do ?
I don 't know .
What would you like to do ?
Got any ideas ?
Mm-mmm .
No ?
Let me think . Let me think .
What can we do ?
We never finished seeing
all the sights in Washington .
We didn 't get to the Lee mansion ,
lots of stuff .
Shall we go sightseeing ...
If it 's a nice day ?
Yeah , let 's do that .
And tomorrow night ,
I 'll take you to a movie , ok ?
Oh , I love you .
I love you , rags .
We 'll have a good day , huh ?
You can bring Mr. Dennings if you like .
Mr. Dennings ?
Well , you know , it 's ok .
Well , thank you very much ,
but why on earth would I want to bring Burke
on your birthday ?
You like him .
Yeah , I like him . Don 't you like him ?
Hey , what 's going on ? What is this , huh ?
You 're going to marry him , aren 't you ?
Oh , God , are you kidding ?
Me marry Burke Dennings ?
Don 't be silly . Of course not .
Where did you get that idea ?
But you like him .
Of course . I like pizzas , too ,
but I 'm not going to marry one .
You don 't like him like daddy ?
Regan , I love your daddy .
I 'll always love your daddy , honey .
Burke just comes around here a lot because ...
Well , he 's lonely .
Don 't got nothin to do .
Well , I heard ... Differently .
Oh , you did ? What did you hear ?
I don 't know . I just thought .
Well , you didn 't think so good .
How do you know ?
Because Burke and I are just friends .
Ok ? Really .
Ok .
You ready for sleep ?
Good night .
Good night , honey .
Jukebox : ¶ lord , I was born a ramblin ' man ¶
¶ lord , I was born a ramblin ' man ¶
it 's my mother , tom .
She 's alone .
I never should have left her .
At least in New York , I 'd be near .
I 'd be close to her .
I could see about a transfer , Damien .
I need reassignment , tom .
I want out of this job . It 's wrong . It 's no good .
You 're the best we 've got .
Am I really ?
It 's more than psychiatry , and you know that , tom .
Some of their problems come down to faith- -
their vocation , the meaning of their lives ,
and I can 't cut it anymore .
I need out . I 'm unfit .
I think I 've lost my faith , tom .
Hello ?
Yes , this is Mrs. MacNeil .
Operator , you have got to be kidding !
I have been on this line for 20 minutes !
Jesus Christ . Can you believe this ?
He doesn 't even call his daughter
on her birthday for Christ 's sake .
Maybe the circuit is busy .
Oh , circuits , my ass ! He doesn 't give a shit !
Why don 't you let me- -
no , I 've got it , Sharon . It 's all right .
Operator , don 't tell me there 's no answer .
It 's the hotel excelsior in Rome .
Would you try it again , please , and let it ring ?
Hello ? Yes .
No , operator ,
I 've given you the number 4 times .
What do you do ,
take an illiteracy test to get that job ?
Don 't tell me to be calm , God damn it !
[ Ring ]
Yeah ?
You 're kidding me .
Ok . I thought I just went to bed .
Yeah .
Hey , what are we doing , scene 61 ?
Ok .
Oh , just remind flo about that blue belt .
Yeah , I 'll see you .
What are you doing here ?
My bed was shaking .
I can 't get to sleep .
Honey .
[ Crash ]
[ Rattle rattle ]
[ Clack ]
God damn it !
Jesus !
[ Crash ]
Aah !
Oh , Karl .
Jesus Christ , Karl , don 't do that .
Very sorry , but you see ...
No rats .
No rats . Thanks a lot . That 's terrific .
[ Church bell ringing ]
Oh , my God .
Ok . Open your fist .
Arm up .
Very good . That wasn 't so bad , was it ?
Lay perfectly still , breathe normally .
Tell me if you feel a vibration .
Regan ?
Do you feel anything ?
Can you feel this ?
I don 't feel anything .
Put this in your mouth .
Keep it there .
This tells your temperature .
When the red light goes on ,
that 's your temperature .
I 'll run it !
[ Regan humming ]
A disorder of the nerves .
At least we think it is .
We don 't know yet exactly how it works .
It 's often seen in early adolescence .
She shows all the symptoms- -
hyperactivity , quick temper ,
performance in math .
Yeah , why the math ? What is that ?
It affects her concentration .
Uh-huh .
Now this is for ritalin .
10 milligrams a day .
Is it like a tranquilizer ?
It 's a stimulant .
A stimulant ?
My God , she 's higher than a kite now .
The condition isn 't quite what it seems .
Nobody knows the cause of hyperkinetic behavior
in a child .
Ritalin seems to work to relieve the condition .
As to how or why , we really don 't know .
But the symptoms could be overreaction to depression .
That 's out of my field .
My daughter isn 't depressed .
Well , you mentioned her father
and the separation .
Do you think I should take her to a psychiatrist ?
No . I think we should wait and see
what happens with the ritalin .
I think that 's the answer .
Ok .
Let 's wait 2 , 3 weeks .
All right . And the lies she 's been telling ,
that 's part of it , huh ?
Lies ?
Like saying her bed 's shaking , that stuff ?
Have you ever known your daughter to swear ,
to use obscenities ?
No , never .
Hmm . Interesting .
Similar ...
Similar to things like her lying ,
it 's uncharacteristic for her- -
I don 't understand . She doesn 't swear .
Well , she let loose quite a string
while I was examining her , Mrs. MacNeil .
I find that hard to believe .
What did she say ?
Her vocabulary is rather extensive .
Well , give me an example .
Like what ? Specifically , what did she say ?
Well , specifically , Mrs. MacNeil ,
she advised me to keep my fingers away
from her ... Goddamn cunt .
I can 't believe it .
Oh .
Now , she- -
you don 't think a psychiatrist ?
No . I think the best explanation
is always the simplest .
Well , we 'll wait . We 'll wait and see .
Ok .
So , in the meantime , try not to worry .
How ?
The edema affected her brain .
You understanding ?
She don 't let no doctor come near her .
She was all the time screaming ,
even talking to the radio .
You should have called me the minute it happened .
Regular hospital not gonna put up with adema ,
so we give her a shot bring her here
till the doctors , they fix up her leg .
Then we take her right out .
2 or 3 months , she 's out , good as new .
Miss ... Yes ?
We want to see Mrs. Karras .
Do you have an appointment ?
Yes .
Are you a relative ?
I 'm her brother . He 's her son .
Just a minute .
[ Woman sobbing ]
You know , it 's funny ...
If you wasn 't a priest ,
you 'd be famous psychiatrist now on park Avenue .
Your mother , she 'd be living in a penthouse instead of ...
You go in , dimmie .
I wait for you outside .
You 'll find Mrs. Karras
in the last bed on the left-hand side .
I 'm so sorry ...
No , no , no .
Come along .
Don 't bother the father .
Go to your bed .
Father , I wanna talk . Let me out .
The father will be back .
It 's all right .
[ Sobbing ]
Mama ...
It 's dimmie , mama .
Dimmie ...
Why you did this to me , dimmie ?
Why ?
Mama , I 'm going to take you out of here .
Mama , I 'm going to take you home .
[ Speaking Greek ]
Everything 's going to be all right .
Mama , I 'm going to take you home .
[ Speaking Greek ]
Couldn 't you put her someplace else ?
Like what , private hospital ?
Who got the money for that , dimmie ...
You ?
There seems to be
an alien pubic hair in my drink .
I beg your pardon ?
Never seen it before in my life .
Have you ?
Well , actually , father ,
we 're pretty comfortable up there ,
at least compared
to the gemini and Mercury programs ,
where they were tight for space .
You see , we 've got about 210 cubic feet ,
so we move around .
If you ever go again , will you take me along ?
What for ?
First missionary on Mars .
Tell me , was it public relations
you did for the gestapo
or community relations ?
I 'm Swiss .
Yes , of course .
And you never went bowling with goebbels , either ,
I suppose ?
Nazi bastard .
Over behind the church .
You know where I mean ? It 's a red-brick wing .
St. Mike 's .
What goes on there ?
Who 's the priest I keep seeing there ?
He 's there all the time .
He has black hair , and he 's intense-looking .
Damien Karras .
That 's his office behind St. Mike 's .
He 's our psychiatric counselor .
Had a pretty rough knock last night , poor guy .
His mother passed away .
She was living by herself ,
and I guess she was dead a couple days
before they found her .
Cunting hun !
Bloody damn butchering Nazi pig !
Stop it !
I 'll kill you !
Aah !
Leave him alone !
Get out ! Get out !
[ Shouting ]
What 's the matter with you ?
What 's for dessert ?
You sleeping ?
[ Drunken singing ]
Whoa !
Steady , big fella .
Ok .
There you go . All right .
Listen , Burke , your car 's at the curb .
Louie 's waiting . It 's nice and warm .
Oh .
Yes , honey , what ?
Fuck !
God . I hope he makes it .
I do , too .
Was he acting up !
Flying is what he was .
Oh , I think we still have ...
¶ Down on the east side of toidy-toid and told ¶
this is a great party .
Yeah . Don 't stop . Keep going .
I don 't need any encouragement .
My idea of heaven is a solid white nightclub
with me as a headliner for all eternity ,
and they love me !
Ohh , boy .
¶ Down on the east side
¶ of toidy-toid and told
¶ that 's my home sweet home
¶ some people think it 's the home of black eyes ¶
¶ just because ...
Hey , I think we 've got a guest .
You 're gonna die up there .
Regan ...
Oh , my God , honey .
Honey , what 's the matter ?
I 'm sorry . She 's been sick .
She didn 't know what she was saying .
Ok .
Excuse me . Come on upstairs .
What made you say that , Regan ?
Do you know , sweetheart ?
Mother ...
What 's wrong with me ?
It 's just like the doctor said .
It 's nerves , and that 's all , ok ?
You just take your pills , and you 'll be fine , really .
Ok ?
Is it coming out , Willi ?
Yes , I think so .
Good .
Aah !
Mother !
[ Thump thump thump ]
[ Gasps ]
Mother !
Help ! Mother !
Mother , make it stop !
Mom !
Aah !
Mother , help me !
One fold .
Big 5 .
Another 5 with a pair .
Just a 10 with 3 clubs ...
And a 6 .
Pair of 3s still bets .
Man : I 'll talk to you about it tomorrow , all right ?
Yeah ?
Where did you get the money for the chivas regal ,
the poor box ?
That 's an insult .
I 've got a vow of poverty .
Where did you get it , then ?
I stole it .
I believe you .
The college president shouldn 't drink .
Tends to set a bad example .
I figure I saved him from a big temptation .
Oh , Christ !
I should have been there , and I wasn 't there ,
and I should have been there .
There was nothing you could do .
Lie down .
Give me the butt .
Come on .
All right . Think you can sleep ?
Yeah .
What , are you going to steal my shoes now ?
No , I tell fortunes by reading the creases .
Now shut up and go to sleep .
Wait .
Good night .
Damien : Stealing is a sin .
[ Damien snoring ]
[ Damien groans ]
Aah !
I don 't want it !
Honey , it 's to help you .
Hold still , baby .
You fucking bastard !
Remember also , oh , lord , thy servant Mary Karras ...
Who has gone before us with the sign of faith
and sleeps the sleep of peace .
Lord , I am not worthy to receive you ,
but only say the word , and I shall be healed .
May the body of Christ bring me to everlasting life .
Well , it 's a symptom ...
Of a type of disturbance
in the chemical-electrical activity of the brain .
In your daughter 's case , in the temporal lobe- -
up here , the lateral part of the brain .
It 's rare ,
but it does cause bizarre hallucinations ,
and usually just before a convulsion .
A convulsion ?
The shaking of the bed .
That 's doubtless due to muscular spasms .
Oh , no . No , no . That was no spasm .
Look , I got on the bed .
The whole bed was thumping
and rising off the floor and shaking .
The whole thing , with me on it .
Your daughter 's problem isn 't her bed .
It 's her brain .
So , um ... What causes this ?
A lesion . A lesion in the temporal lobe .
It 's a kind of seizure disorder .
Look , doc , I really don 't understand
how her whole personality could change .
In the temporal lobe , it 's very common .
It can last for days or even weeks .
It isn 't rare to find destructive ,
even criminal behavior .
Hey , do me a favor . Tell me something good .
Don 't be alarmed .
If it 's a lesion , in a way she 's fortunate .
All we have to do is remove the scar .
Let 's move her .
Regan , can you sit up
and scoot over here ?
A little more .
Good .
I 'm just going to move you down on the table , ok ?
It 's just for a short time .
You 're doing fine .
Very sticky .
Now , Regan , you 're going to feel something
a little bit cold and wet .
Ok , you 're going to feel a little stick here .
Don 't move .
Mm ...
Good .
Ok , you 're going to feel some pressure here .
Now , don 't move .
Aah ...
Hmm ...
Agh ...
Mm ...
Ah !
Hook up .
[ Very loud clacking ]
Ah !
There 's nothing there .
No vascular displacement at all .
You want me to run another series ?
I don 't think so .
No . I 'd like you to see her again .
Excuse me , doctor .
Chris MacNeil is on the phone .
She says it 's urgent .
You got some time ?
Of course .
[ Doorbell rings ]
[ Regan screaming upstairs ]
Dr. Klein ?
Yes , I 'm Dr. Klein . This is Dr. tanney .
I 'm Sharon .
Things have gotten worse since we phoned you .
Is she having spasms again ?
Yeah , but they 've gotten violent .
Did you give her the medication I gave you ?
Yes .
What was that ?
Thorazine .
Before that , it was ritalin .
Regan : Aah ! Aah ! Aah !
Chris , doctors .
Mrs. MacNeil , I 'm Dr. tanney .
What is it ? What 's happening ?
Make it stop ! It 's burning !
Chris : Do something . Please , help her .
Oh , please , mother !
Mother !
Make it stop ! He 's trying to kill me !
Mother ! Mother !
Aah ! Aah !
Aah !
[ Gurgling ]
All right . Let 's see what- -
[ demonic voice ] Keep away !
The sow is mine !
Fuck me ! Fuck me !
Fuck me !
Aah !
No !
Stay away from me !
Stay away !
No !
Mother , please !
Hold her tight .
Don 't let them ! No !
[ Wailing ]
Aah !
She 's heavily sedated .
She 'll probably sleep through tomorrow .
What was going on in there ?
How could she fly off the bed like that ?
Pathological states
can induce abnormal strength ...
Accelerated motor performance .
For example ,
say a 90-pound woman sees her child
pinned under the wheel of a truck ,
runs out and lifts the wheels
1 / 2 foot up off the ground .
You 've heard the story . Same thing here .
Same principle , I mean .
So what 's wrong with her ?
We still think the temporal lobe .
What are you talking about , for Christ 's sakes ?
Did you see her or not ? !
She 's acting like she 's fucking out of her mind ,
psychotic like a split personality , or ...
Oh , Jesus . I 'm sorry .
There haven 't been more than 100 authentic cases
of so-called split personality ,
Mrs. MacNeil .
Now , I know the temptation
is to leap to psychiatry ,
but any reasonable psychiatrist
would exhaust the somatic possibilities first .
So what 's next ?
Another encephalogram , I would think ,
to pin down that lesion .
It will involve another spinal .
Oh , Christ !
Now , what we missed in the e.E.G.
And the arteriograms
could conceivably turn up there .
At least it would eliminate
certain other possibilities .
Aah ...
Dr. tanney says the x-rays are negative .
In other words , normal .
Do you keep any drugs in your house ?
No , of course not .
Nothing like that .
Are you sure ?
Well , of course I 'm sure .
I 'd tell you .
Christ ! I don 't even smoke grass .
Are you planning to be home soon ?
I mean , uh ... To L.A. , I mean .
Um ...
No , I , uh ...
I 'm building a new house .
My old one 's been sold .
I don 't know ...
I was going to take ...
I was going to take Regan to Europe for a while
after she finished school .
Why do you ask ?
I think it 's time
we started looking for a psychiatrist .
[ Siren ]
[ Telephone rings ]
[ Ring ]
Hello ?
Shar ?
[ Siren passing ]
Shit .
God .
[ Door closes ]
Sharon !
What the hell do you mean
going off and leaving Regan by herself ?
[ Doorbell rings ]
Didn 't he tell you ?
Didn 't who tell me ?
Burke .
What 's Burke got to do with it ?
There wasn 't anybody here ,
so when I went to get the thorazine ,
I had him stay with her . I should 've known better .
Yeah , I guess you should have .
How were the tests ?
We have to start looking for a shrink .
Hi , Chuck . Come on in .
I suppose you heard .
Heard what ?
You haven 't heard .
Burke 's dead .
He must have been drunk .
He fell down the steps right outside .
When he hit " m " street , he broke his neck .
Oh , God !
[ Sobbing ]
No !
Yeah , I know .
Sharon ...
Oh , my God .
When I touch your forehead ,
open your eyes .
Are you comfortable , Regan ?
Yes .
How old are you ?
12 .
Is there someone inside you ?
Sometimes .
Who is it ?
I don 't know .
Is it captain howdy ?
If I ask him to tell me ,
will you let him answer ?
No .
Why not ?
I 'm afraid .
If he talks to me , I think he 'll leave you .
Do you want him to leave you ?
Yes .
I 'm speaking to the person inside of Regan now .
If you are there , you , too , are hypnotized ,
and must answer all my questions .
Come forward ...
And answer me now .
[ Growling ]
Aargh !
Are you the person inside of Regan ?
Psychiatrist : Who are you ?
Aagh !
Aah !
Harold !
Let go !
Aaaaaah !
Father Karras ?
Have we met ?
No , we haven 't met ,
but they said I could tell- -
that you look like a boxer .
William F. Kinderman , homicide .
What 's this all about ?
Yeah , it 's true ,
you do look like a boxer .
Like ... John garfield in body and soul .
Exactly . John garfield .
People tell you that , father ?
Do people tell you you look like Paul Newman ?
Always .
You know this director was doing a film here- -
Burke Dennings ?
I 've seen him .
You 've seen him .
And you 're also familiar how last week he died ?
Only what I read in the papers .
Father , what do you know
on the subject of witchcraft ?
From the witching end , not the hunting .
I once did a paper on it .
Really ?
From the psychiatric end .
I know . I read it .
Father , this desecration in the church- -
do you think this
has anything to do with witchcraft ?
Maybe .
Some rituals used in a black mass , maybe .
And now , Dennings ...
You read how he died ?
In a fall .
Let me tell you how ,
and please , father ...
Confidential .
Burke Dennings , good father ,
was found at the bottom of those steps
leading to " m " street
with his head turned completely around ,
facing backwards .
Didn 't it happen in the fall ?
It 's possible .
Possible , however ...
Unlikely .
Exactly .
So on the one hand , we 've got a ...
Witchcraft kind of murder ,
and on the other hand ,
a black mass-type desecration
in the church .
You think the killer and the desecrater
are the same ?
Maybe somebody crazy ,
somebody with a spite against the church ,
some unconscious rebellion .
Sick priest , is that it ?
Look , father , this is hard for you .
Please , I understand ,
but for priests on the campus here ,
you 're the psychiatrist .
You 'd know who was sick at the time , who wasn 't- -
I mean , this kind of sickness .
You 'd know that .
I don 't know anyone who fits that description .
Ahh .
Doctor 's ethics .
If you knew , you wouldn 't tell ?
No , I probably wouldn 't .
Not to bother you with trivia ,
but a psychiatrist- -
in sunny California , no less- -
was put in jail for not telling the police
what he knew about a patient .
Is that a threat ?
No . I mention it only in passing .
Incidentally- -
I mention it only in passing- -
I could always tell the judge
it was a matter of confession .
Hey , father ! Wait a minute !
Do you like movies ?
Very much .
Well , I get passes to the best shows .
Mrs. K. , she gets tired , never likes to go .
That 's too bad .
Yeah . I hate to go alone .
You know , I love to talk film ...
Discuss , to critique .
You want to see a film with me ?
I got passes to the crest .
It 's Othello .
Who 's in it ?
Debbie Reynolds , Desdemona , and Othello , Groucho Marx .
You happy ?
I 've seen it .
One last time .
You can think of some priest who fits the bill ?
Come on .
No , answer the question , father paranoia .
All right ...
All right .
You know who I think really did it ?
Who ?
The Dominicans . Go pick on them .
I could have you deported , you know that ?
I lied .
You look like sal mineo .
It looks like a type of disorder
that 's rarely ever seen anymore ,
except in primitive cultures .
We ... We call it
somnambuliform possession .
Quite frankly ,
we really don 't know much about it at all ,
except that it ... It starts with a ...
Conflict or a guilt ,
and leads to the patient 's delusions
that his body has been invaded
by some alien intelligence ,
uh ... A spirit , if you will .
Look , I 'm telling you again ,
and you better believe me ,
I am not locking her up in some God damn asylum .
Well , it 's not- -
and I don 't care what you call it ,
I 'm not putting her away !
I 'm sorry , ma 'am .
You 're sorry ?
Jesus Christ !
88 doctors ,
and all you can tell me with all your bullshit is- -
of course , there is ...
One outside chance for a cure .
But , uh ...
I think of it as ...
Shock treatment .
As I said , it 's a very outside chance .
Would you just name it , for God 's sakes ?
What is it ?
Do you have any religious beliefs ?
No .
What about your daughter ?
Why ?
Have you heard of exorcism ?
Well , it 's a ...
Stylized ritual in which the , uh ...
Rabbi or the priest try to drive out
the so-called invading spirit .
It 's been pretty much discarded these days ,
except by the catholics ,
who keep it in the closet as sort of an embarrassment ,
but it has worked , in fact ,
although not for the reasons they think .
It 's purely , uh ... Force of suggestion .
The , uh , victim 's belief in possession
is what helped cause it , so in that same way ,
the belief in the power of exorcism
can make it disappear .
You 're telling me
that I should take my daughter
to a witch doctor .
Is that it ?
Karl ?
Did you put this in Regan 's bedroom ?
She 's going to be well ?
Karl , if you put this in Regan 's bedroom ,
I want you to tell me . Now , did you ?
No , not me .
I did not .
This was under Regan 's pillow .
Did you put it there ?
Of course I didn 't .
I didn 't put it .
Karl : Excuse me , madam .
What ?
A man to see you .
What man ?
Might your daughter remember , perhaps ,
if Mr. Dennings was in her room that night ?
Why do you ask ?
Might she remember ?
No .
No , she was heavily sedated .
It 's serious ?
Yes , I 'm afraid it is .
May I ask- -
we still don 't know .
Watch out for drafts .
A draft in the fall ,
when the house is hot ,
is a magic carpet for bacteria .
Excuse me , madam . Anything else ?
No , Karl . We 're fine . Thank you .
It 's all right . Go .
Why are you asking all this ?
It 's strange .
The deceased comes to visit ,
stays only 20 minutes ,
and leaves all alone a very sick girl .
And speaking plainly , Mrs. MacNeil ,
it isn 't likely he would ...
Fall from a window .
Besides ,
a fall wouldn 't do to his neck
what we found ,
except maybe 1 chance in 1,000 .
No . My hunch- -
my ... Opinion- -
he was killed by a very powerful man .
Point one .
And the fracturing of his skull ,
point two ,
plus the other things we mentioned ,
would make it very probable- -
probable , not certain- -
that the deceased was killed
and then pushed from your daughter 's window .
But nobody was in the room
except your daughter ,
so how can this be ?
It could be one way .
If someone came calling
between the time miss Spencer left
and the time you returned .
Judas priest , just a second .
The servants ? They have visitors ?
Not at all .
You were expecting a package that day ,
some delivery ?
None that I know of .
Groceries , cleaning- - a package ?
I really wouldn 't know .
Karl takes care of all that .
I see .
Would you like to ask him ?
No , never mind . It 's ...
It 's very remote .
No , never mind .
Yep .
Would you like some more coffee ?
Please .
That 's cute .
Your daughter , she 's the artist ?
Thank you .
You 're welcome .
Incidentally , uh ...
You might ask your daughter
if she remembers seeing Mr. Dennings
in her room that night .
He wouldn 't have any reason in the world
to go up to her room .
Oh , I know , I realize , but ...
If certain British doctors never asked ,
" what is this fungus , "
we wouldn 't today have penicillin , correct ?
Well ...
When she 's better , I 'll ask her .
Yeah , couldn 't hurt .
Uh , in the meantime ...
That 's ok .
Uh , I really hate to ask you this , but ...
What ?
For my daughter ,
could you please give an autograph ?
Of course .
Um ... Where 's a pencil ?
Right here . Here .
Oh ... She 'd love it .
And what 's her name ?
I lied .
It 's for me .
The spelling is on the back .
Kinderman .
Oh , you know that film you made , um ...
Angel ?
Oh , yeah .
I saw that 6 times .
Really ?
Ha ha ! Thank you .
You 're a very nice lady .
Thank you .
You 're a nice man .
I 'll come back when she 's feeling better .
Bye .
[ Crash ]
Regan : Please , no !
[ Demonic voice ] Do it !
Please , no !
[ Demonic voice ] You bitch ! Do it !
Regan : No , please ! No !
Aaah !
Stop it !
[ Demonic voice ] Let Jesus fuck you !
Let Jesus fuck you !
Let him fuck you !
Aaaah !
Give it ! Give it to me !
Stop ! Stop it !
Lick me !
Oh !
Aaaah !
Chris !
Mrs. MacNeil !
[ Pounding on door ]
Oh ! Oh !
Aah !
Open the door !
[ Demonic voice ] Do you know what she did ...
Your cunting daughter ?
[ Wailing ]
Chris MacNeil ?
Please go away .
I 'm father Karras .
I 'm very sorry . Hello .
It 's all right .
I should have told you I wouldn 't be in uniform .
Yeah , that would have helped .
Have you got a cigarette , father ?
Sure .
Thanks .
Cold .
Yeah .
Uh ...
How did a shrink ever get to be a priest ?
It 's the other way around .
The society sent me through medical school .
Oh . Where ?
Harvard , bellevue ...
Johns Hopkins- -
places like that .
I see .
You 're a friend of father Dyer 's , right ?
Yes , I am .
Pretty close ?
Pretty close .
Did he talk to you about my party ?
He sure did .
About my daughter ?
No . I didn 't know you had one .
He didn 't mention her ?
No .
Oh .
He didn 't tell you what she did ?
He didn 't mention her .
Priests are pretty tight-mouthed , then , huh ?
That depends .
On what ?
The priest .
Sure .
I mean , what if a person ...
Uh , came to ... You know ,
that was a murderer or criminal of some kind ,
and they ...
And they wanted some kind of help .
Would you have to turn him in ?
If he came to me for spiritual advice ,
I 'd say no .
You wouldn 't .
No , I wouldn 't .
But I would try to convince him
to turn himself in .
And , uh ...
How do you go about getting an exorcism ?
I beg your pardon ?
If , um ...
If a person 's ,
you know , possessed by a demon or something ,
how do they get an exorcism ?
I 'd have to get them into a time machine
and get them back to the 16th century .
I didn 't get you .
It just doesn 't happen anymore .
Oh , yeah ? Since when ?
Since we learned about mental illness ,
paranoia , schizophrenia ,
all those things
they taught me in Harvard .
Since the day I joined the jesuits ,
I 've never met one priest
who has performed an exorcism . Not one .
Yeah , well ...
Ahem ... It just so happens
that somebody very close to me is ...
Is probably possessed
and needs an exorcist .
Father Karras , it 's my little girl .
[ Sobs ]
And that 's all the more reason
to forget about exorcism .
Why ? I don 't understand .
It could make things worse .
Secondly , the church ,
before it approves an exorcism ,
conducts an investigation to see if it 's warranted .
That takes time .
You could do it yourself .
No , I couldn 't .
I need church approval , and that 's rarely given .
Well ...
Could you see her ?
Yes , I could .
I could see her as a psychiatrist- -
not a psychiatrist ! She needs a priest !
She 's already seen
every fucking psychiatrist in the world
and they sent me to you !
Now you 're gonna send me back to them ?
Jesus Christ ! Won 't somebody help me ?
No , you don 't understand . Your daughter- -
can 't you help her ? Just help her !
[ Regan moaning and wailing ]
It wants no straps .
Hello , Regan .
I 'm a friend of your mother 's .
I 'd like to help you .
You might loosen the straps , then .
I 'm afraid you might hurt yourself , Regan .
I am not Regan .
I see .
Well , then , let 's introduce ourselves .
I 'm Damien Karras .
And I 'm the devil !
Now kindly undo these straps .
If you 're the devil ,
why not make the straps disappear ?
That 's much too vulgar a display of power , Karras .
Where 's Regan ?
In here ... With us .
Show me Regan ,
and I 'll loosen one of the straps .
[ Old man 's voice ] Can you help
an old altar boy , father ?
Your mother 's in here with us , Karras .
Would you like to leave a message ?
I 'll see that she gets it .
If that 's true ...
Then you must know my mother 's maiden name .
What is it ?
Thank you .
Look , I 'm only against the possibility
of doing your daughter more harm than good .
Nothing you could do
could make it any worse .
I can 't do it .
I need evidence
the church would accept as signs of possession .
Like what ?
Like her speaking in a language
she 's never studied .
What else ?
I don 't know .
I 'd have to look it up .
Thought you were supposed to be an expert .
There are no experts .
You probably know as much about possession
as most priests .
Your daughter doesn 't say she 's a demon .
She says she 's the devil himself .
If you 've seen as many psychotics as I have ,
you 'd realize that 's the same thing
as saying you 're Napoleon Bonaparte .
You asked me ...
What I think is best for your daughter .
6 months under observation ...
In the best hospital you can find .
You show me Regan 's double- -
same face , same voice , everything ...
And I 'd know it wasn 't Regan .
I 'd know in my gut .
I 'm telling you that thing upstairs isn 't my daughter .
I want you to tell me that you know for a fact
there 's nothing wrong with my daughter
except in her mind !
You tell me you know for a fact
that an exorcism wouldn 't do any good !
You tell me that !
Did Regan know a priest was coming over ?
No .
Did you know my mother died recently ?
Yes , I did . I 'm sorry .
No ... Is Regan aware of it ?
Not at all .
Why do you ask ?
It 's not important . Good night .
Regan 's voice : Hello ?
[ Indistinct ]
Regan : Ok , um , hello , daddy .
This is me !
What should I say ?
Chris : Well , go on , just talk to your daddy ,
anything you want .
All right , um ...
Tell him what you 've been doing ...
Uh , well , you see , um ...
I mean I hope you can hear me .
Can you hear me ok ?
Well , let me see .
Uh ... [ Laughs ]
Chris : Go on , talk to your daddy .
Oh , I don 't know what to say .
Uh , well , first we--no ... Wait .
I don 't know !
Oh , Regan .
Tell him about Washington .
Ok . See , we 're in Washington now , daddy .
He broke the bread , gave it to his disciples ,
and said ...
" Take this , all of you , and eat it ... "
" For this is my body . "
When the supper was ended , he took the cup .
Again he gave you thanks and praise ,
gave the cup to his disciples ,
and said , " take this , all of you ,
and drink from it ... "
" This is the cup of my blood- -
" the blood of the new and everlasting covenant- -
the mystery of faith . "
What an excellent day for an exorcism .
You 'd like that ?
Intensely .
But wouldn 't that drive you out of Regan ?
It would bring us together .
You and Regan ?
You and us .
Did you do that ?
Uh-huh ...
Do it again .
In time .
No , now .
Mirabile dictu , don 't you agree ?
You speak Latin ?
Ego te absolvo .
Quod nomen mihi est ?
Bonjour .
LA plume de ma tante .
How long you planning to stay in Regan ?
Until she rots and lies stinking in the earth .
What 's that ?
Holy water .
You keep it away .
Uhh ! Aah ! It burns !
Oh ! It burns !
Aah !
A-a-a-aah !
[ Speaking in tongues ]
Who are you ?
A-a-a-a-aah !
Chris : No , I 'm in , like , uh , seclusion .
No . I 'm just exhausted from work .
Um ... She 's ... She 's fine .
She just isn 't , uh ...
I don 't want to talk about it , ok ?
Um ...
Ok . I 'll talk to you , huh ?
I 'll call you as soon as it 's over .
No , I 'm just--I really- -
I 'm going through something , and I just have to , uh ...
No , no .
No , no . There 's nothing .
Hey , thanks a lot .
Bye , now .
[ Hangs up telephone ]
Want a drink ?
Please .
What do you drink ?
Uh , scotch ...
With ice , water .
Ok .
No ice .
I 'll get some from the kitchen .
No , it 's all right . I 'll take it straight .
That 's fine . Please , sit .
Really ? You sure ?
Yes . Sit .
Where 's her father ?
In Europe .
Have you told him what 's happened ?
No .
Well , I think you should .
I told Regan that was holy water .
I sprinkled it on her ,
and she reacted very violently .
It 's tap water .
What 's the difference ?
Holy water is blessed ,
and that doesn 't help support
a case for possession .
She ...
Killed Burke Dennings .
What ?
She killed Burke Dennings .
She pushed him out her window .
Recording : [ Speaking in tongues ]
Damien : Who are you ?
[ Speaking in tongues ]
It 's a language , all right .
It 's English .
What do you mean , English ?
It 's English in reverse . Listen .
Give us time !
Let her die .
Recording : I am no one .
I am no one !
Fear the priest !
Fear the priest .
Ooh ... Merrin .
[ Stops tape ]
[ Rewinds tape ]
I am no one !
Ooh ...
Merrin ! Fear the priest !
[ Telephone rings ]
Merrin !
Yeah ?
Yeah .
I 'll be right there .
I don 't want Chris to see this .
What 's wrong ? What is it ?
Shh ...
You 're convinced that it 's genuine ?
I don 't know .
No , not really , I suppose ,
but I have made a prudent judgment
that it meets the conditions
set down in the ritual .
You 'd want to do the exorcism yourself ?
Yes .
It might be best to have a man of experience- -
someone who 's spent time in foreign missions .
I understand , your excellency .
Let 's see who 's around .
In the meantime ,
I 'll call you as soon as I know .
Thank you , your excellency .
Well , he does know the background .
I doubt there 's any danger
in just having him assist .
Should be a psychiatrist present , anyway .
What about the exorcist ? Have you any ideas ?
How about lankester Merrin ?
Merrin ?
I had the notion he was in Iraq .
I read that he was working on a dig near ninevah .
Yeah , you 're right , Mike , but he 's finished .
He came back 3 or 4 months ago .
He 's at Woodstock now .
What 's he doing there , teaching ?
No . He 's working on another book .
Don 't you think he 's too old , tom ?
How 's his health ?
He must be all right- -
still running around digging up tombs .
Mmm .
Besides , he 's had experience .
I didn 't know that .
10 , 12 years ago , I think , in Africa .
The exorcism supposedly lasted months .
I heard it damn near killed him .
Father ?
Mrs. MacNeil ?
Yes .
I 'm Father Merrin .
Come in .
Thank you .
Is father Karras here ?
Father .
Father Karras .
It 's an honor to meet you , father .
[ Demonic voice ] M-e-e-errin !
Are you very tired ?
No .
I 'd like you to go quickly to the residence
and gather a cassock for myself ,
two surplices , a purple stole ,
and some holy water ,
and your copy of the Roman ritual- -
the large one .
I believe we should begin .
Do you want to hear
the background of the case first ?
Why ?
Radio : It 's yours to do with as you please .
You can choose to escape if you want ,
but you may never be able to return .
Don 't let anyone decide for you .
[ Turns radio off ]
[ Strange moaning sounds from Regan ]
[ Whispering a prayer ]
Thank you .
Thank you very much .
You 're welcome .
Would you like some Brandy in that , father ?
Well , the doctors say I shouldn 't .
But , thank God , my will is weak .
Especially important is the warning
to avoid conversations with the demon .
We may ask what is relevant ,
but anything beyond that is dangerous .
He 's a liar . The demon is a liar .
He will lie to confuse us ...
But he will also mix lies with the truth ...
To attack us .
The attack is psychological ,
Damien ...
And powerful ...
So don 't listen .
Remember that- - do not listen .
I think it might be helpful to give you some background
on the personalities Regan has manifested .
So far , I 'd say there seem to be 3 .
She 's convinced that- -
there is only one .
[ Demonic groaning ]
[ Howling ]
What is your daughter 's middle name , Mrs. MacNeil ?
Teresa .
What a lovely name .
[ Growling ]
Stick your cock up her ass ,
you motherfucking ,
worthless cocksucker !
Be silent !
Aah !
Ohh .
Aaah !
" Our father , who art in heaven- - "
" hallowed be thy name . Thy kingdom come ,
" thy will be done
" on earth as it is in heaven .
" Give us this day our daily bread .
" Forgive us our trespasses
" as we forgive those who trespass against us .
Lead us not into temptation ... "
" But deliver us from the evil one . "
" Save me , oh , God , by thy name .
By thy might , defend my cause . "
" Proud men have risen up against me ,
" and men of violence seek my life .
" But God is my helper .
" The lord sustains my life .
" In every need he has delivered me .
" Glory be to the father and to the son
and to the holy spirit . "
" As it was in the beginning , is now , and ever shall be
without end . Amen . "
" Save your servant ... "
" Who places her trust in thee , my God . "
" Be unto her a fortified tower ... "
" In the face of the enemy . "
Arr ! Aah !
" Let the enemy have no power over me . "
" Let the enemy be powerless to harm her . "
Your mother sucks cocks in hell , Karras !
" The lord be with you . "
" And also with you . "
Let us pray .
" Holy lord , almighty father ,
" everlasting God , and father of our lord ,
" Jesus Christ ,
" who once and for all
" consigned that fallen tyrant
" to the flames of hell ,
" who sent your only begotten son
" into the world
" to crush that roaring lion ,
" hasten to our call for help
" and snatch from ruination
" and from the clutches
" of the noonday devil
" this human being
" made in your image and likeness .
" Strike terror into the beast
" now laying waste to your vineyard .
" Let your mighty hand cast him out
" of your servant , Regan Teresa MacNeil ,
" so he may no longer hold captive this person
whom pleased you to make in your image . "
Aaah !
" And to redeem through your son ,
" who lives and reigns with you
" in the unity of the holy spirit ,
God forever and ever . "
Amen .
" Oh , lord , hear my prayer . "
[ Moaning ]
Father Karras .
[ Groaning ]
Damien !
The response , please , Damien !
" Let my cry come unto thee . "
" Almighty lord , word of God the father ,
" and Jesus Christ ,
" God and lord of all creation ,
" who gave to your holy apostles
" the power to tramp underfoot
" serpents and scorpions ,
grant me , your unworthy servant- - "
bastards ! Stop !
" Pardon for my sins
and the power to confront this cruel demon . "
Aaah !
[ Howling ]
See the cross of the lord .
Be gone , you hostile power !
O lord , hear my prayer .
Let my cry come unto thee .
The lord be with you .
And also with you .
[ Wheezing ]
Ha ha ha !
Father .
Ha ha !
[ Coughing ]
Ha ha ha !
Ha ha ha .
I cast you out , unclean spirit- -
shove it up your ass , faggot !
In the name of our lord Jesus Christ !
It is he who commands you !
He who flung you
from the heights of heaven to the depths of hell !
Fuck him !
Be gone from this creature of God !
Be gone !
In the name of the father
and of the son and the holy spirit ,
by this sign of the holy cross
of our lord Jesus Christ ,
who lives and reigns with the father
and the holy spirit !
Damien !
Amen .
God , defender of the human race- -
oh !
Look down in pity- -
you killed your mother !
You left her alone to die !
Shut up !
She 'll never forgive you . You killed her !
Bastard !
I command you ,
by the judge
of the living and the dead ,
to depart from this servant of God .
It 's the power- -
holy water .
Oh !
It 's the power of Christ
that compels you !
The power of Christ compels you !
He brought you low
by his bloodstained quest .
Do not despise my command
because you know me to be sinner .
It is God himself who commands you ...
The majestic Christ
who commands you .
God the father commands you .
Grrrr !
God , the son ,
commands you .
Aaah !
God the holy spirit commands you .
The mystery of the cross commands you .
The blood of the martyrs commands you .
Oh !
Aah !
[ Howling ]
Give way to Christ , you prince of murderers .
You 're guilty before almighty God ,
guilty before his son ,
guilty before the whole human race .
It 's the lord who expels you ,
he who is coming to judge
both the living and the dead
and the world by fire .
Are you tired ?
Let 's rest before we start again .
[ Wheezing ]
Why this girl ?
Doesn 't make sense .
I think the point is to make us despair ...
To see ourselves as ...
Animal and ugly .
To reject the possibility that God could love us .
Will you excuse me , Damien ?
Grrrr !
[ Voice of Karras ' mother ] Dimmie ...
Why you do this to me ?
Please , dimmie .
I 'm afraid .
You 're not my mother .
Dimmie , please .
What is it ?
Her heart .
Can you give her something ?
She 'll go into a coma .
[ Speaking Greek ]
You 're not my mother !
Don 't listen .
Why , dimmie ?
Damien !
Dimmie , please .
Damien .
Get out .
Grrrr !
" Our father ,
who art in heaven , hallowed be thy name ... "
Is it over ?
Is she gonna die ?
No .
[ Doorbell rings ]
You son of a bitch !
Ohh !
Take me !
Come into me !
God damn you !
Take me !
[ Regan crying ]
No !
[ Regan screaming ]
Mother !
[ Sobbing ] Mother ...
Somebody fell here !
On the steps here !
[ Sirens ]
Mother !
Regan ?
[ Sobbing ]
Do you want to make your confession ?
Are you sorry for having offended God
and for all the sins of your past life ?
Ego te absolvo de peccatos tuus
in nomine patris et filii et ...
Spiritus sanctu . Amen .
Where do you want this ?
What is it ?
Phonograph ?
Storage .
That 's everything .
I 'll miss you .
Same here .
Sure you won 't change your mind ?
I found this in her room .
Better hurry .
Yeah .
Regan ! Come on , honey . We have to get going .
She doesn 't remember any of it .
That 's good .
All done .
Ok . Honey , this is father Dyer .
Hi , father .
Hello .
Ready , missus .
Goodbye , father .
Goodbye .
I 'll call you .
Bye .
Bye , father .
I hope I see you again .
I hope so , too .
Father Dyer !
I thought you 'd like to keep this .
Why don 't you keep it .
Lieutenant ...
You just missed them .
How 's the girl ?
She seemed fine .
That 's important .
Well ... Well ...
Back to business , back to work .
Bye , father .
Goodbye .
Father Dyer .
Do you go to films ?
Sure .
Well , I got passes .
In fact , I got a pass to the crest
tomorrow night . Would you like to go ?
What 's playing ?
Wuthering Heights .
Who 's in it ?
Heathcliff , Jackie Gleason .
And in the role of Catherine earnshaw ,
Lucille Ball .
I 've seen it .
Another one .
Had your lunch ?
No .